{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "William Juxon recorded this man's last speech, and John Cook declared the prosecution of this man as fighting \"tyranny itself.\" Some of this man's last words before reaching the Banqueting House were to his children, Henry of Oatlands and Elizabeth Stuart. Colonel Francis Hacker took this man to his death, before which this man cryptically uttered \"remember.\" Either William Hulet or Richard Brandon were responsible for beheading, for ten points, what English king, the only one to be executed?",
      "answer": "Charles I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Adrastus, King of Argos, vows to never invade this city at the end of the play The Suppliants. This city’s leader, Peisistratus, funded its Dionysia festivals, during which Thespis became the first named man to represent a character on stage. In a namesake play, a resident of this city-state named Lysistrata plots to halt the ongoing Peloponnesian War by convincing Greek wives to stop sleeping with their husbands. For ten points, name this city-state, the home of Aristophanes, whose Theatre of Dionysus was built on its Acropolis.",
      "answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man became known as the “Marble Model” due to his low number of demerits at West Point and his statuesque demeanor. This man's order to dig ditches around one city led him to be called the “King of Spades,” and this man's extreme caution in battle led his soldiers to refer to him as “Granny.” During the West Virginia campaign, this man was given the sobriquet “Evacuating” after a defeat at Cheat Mountain. Preceded as a general by his father who was himself nicknamed “Light-Horse,\" for ten points, who was this Confederate Civil War general?",
      "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas van Orden challenged the display of the Ten Commandments in this state's Capitol. During the tenure of a governor of this state who also served as Secretary of Energy under Donald Trump, a thirteen-hour filibuster against the anti-abortion Senate Bill 5 was launched by Wendy Davis. In 2021, a senator from this state came under fire for travelling to a Ritz-Carlton in Mexico while over 4.3 million of this state's citizens were without power. Rick Perry and Ted Cruz are both politicians from, for ten points, what U.S. state?",
      "answer": "Texas 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Heather Penney and Marc Sasseville were tasked with thwarting the initial goal of this event, and Mike Pence carries a copy of A Life of Integrity with him when he travels in order to commemorate this event. Resistance from a group of 40 crew members and passengers during this event forced the central vehicle down in Somerset County, Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this event involving the hijacking of a plane that terrorists intended to crash into Washington, D.C, after similar attacks on the Pentagon and the Twin Towers.",
      "answer": "Hijacking of United Airlines Flight 93"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, the Society for the Suppression of Vice encouraged a police raid of the Everard Baths. Over two dozen men were arrested in this state's anti-gay Ariston Bathhouse raid. This state banned sexual orientation discrimination via the SONDA, and this state legalized same-sex marriage in the Marriage Equality Act in 2011. Dick Leitsch [[LEECH]] led a \"Sip-in\" in this state, and Dave van Ronk was barricaded in a bar during protests in this state's Greenwich Village. For ten points, name this state in which the Stonewall Riots took place.",
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country attempted to overthrow Raúl Leoni in the Machurucuto Incident in Venezuela. This country, which led Operation Carlota, won the Battle of Quifangondo with the MPLA while fighting South African Defense Forces in Angola. Due to the end of Comecon [[KOH-meh-kohn]], this country faced the Maleconazo protests and shifted to organopónicos agriculture during its Special Period. One key leader in the overthrow of this country's Fulgencio Batista was Argentine revolutionary Che Guevara. For ten points, name this Caribbean island nation.",
      "answer": "Republic of Cuba or República de Cuba"
    },
    {
      "question": "A historian from this country was told, “Your criticism of me would damage your reputation as a historian, if you had one” during a 1961 debate. That historian from this country verified that Hitler did not escape Berlin in the late days of the war and controversially claimed that the supposed Hitler Diaries were real. A.J.P. Taylor, who was from this country, created popular television lectures that led to him being compared with this country's Thomas Babington Macaulay. For ten points, name this country in which history broadcasts were run by the BBC.",
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
        "UK",
        "Great Britain",
        "England 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1811, this state's \"revolution from above\" freed serfs, allowing peasants to own farmland through the Edict of Regulation. This state was addressed in the 1813 \"To my People\" speech, and Stein and Hardenberg reformed this state, as did Theodor von Schön [[SHUHN]]. This state created Berlin University, where Johann Gottlieb Fichte [[FIK-tuh]] taught. When this state's Queen Louise died, Napoleon claimed the king lost \"his best minister.\" Wilhelm von Humboldt created the new humanism movement in, for ten points, what German kingdom?",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Prussia",
        "Königreich Preussen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man's presidency the House launched an investigation into the conduct of General James Wilkinson. This man disapproved of the 1809 Treaty of Fort Wayne, an agreement to purchase Native American land which led to the outbreak of Tecumseh’s War. This man was forced to evacuate the White House due to a British invasion of Washington, D.C. during the War of 1812. For ten points, name this man who succeeded Thomas Jefferson and served as America’s fourth president.",
      "answer": "James Madison, Jr. 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first person in a family to become one of these people was referred to by a term meaning “new man.” These people continued to serve under Odoacer [[oh-doh-AH-ker]] before ultimately ceasing to exist in the West in the seventh century. The Gracchi [[GRAH- kee]] weakened the power of these people, whose “ultimate decrees” could transfer absolute control to the consul. Usually 300 to 500 of these people served at a time, and they were initially all patricians. Given terms for life, for ten points, who were these Roman legislators?",
        "answer": "Senators"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While the Senate ended in the West in the 7th century, it continued on in Constantinople until the 13th century, beginning its move to the East under the rule of this \"Great\" 6th century Byzantine emperor who rewrote Roman law and is sometimes called the \"Last Roman.\"",
        "answer": "Justinian I or Justinian the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this family called in his state’s National Guard to deal with a riot that began after 83 partiers were arrested at a bar on 12th Street. That member of this family criticized a group of companies known as the “Big Three,” calling them “gas-guzzling dinosaurs.” Another of this family's members served as CEO of Bain Capital and claimed to have hired “binders full of women.” That man from this family replaced Orrin Hatch in the Senate eight years after unsuccessfully running with Paul Ryan for president. For ten points, name this Mormon family which includes George and Mitt.",
        "answer": "Romney family or the Romneys"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "George Romney's granddaughter, Ronna McDaniel, has been a staunch supporter of Donald Trump and was elected in 2017 to be the second female chair of this organization which leads Trump's party.",
        "answer": [
          "Republican National Committee",
          "RNC 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Della Torre family made a bid to rule this city during the war between the Guelphs [[GWELFS]] and Ghibellines [[GIH-bih-lines]] until their defeat at Desio [[DEH- syoh]]. Following a war of succession in this city, members of the University of Pavia established the short-lived Golden Ambrosian Republic. That republic founded in this city was abolished by the condottiero-turned-duke, Francesco Sforza, who later signed the Peace at Lodi [[LOH-dee]] with Naples and Florence. For ten points, name this northern Italian city, known to the Romans as Mediolanum.",
        "answer": [
          "Milan or Milano",
          "Mediolanum before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Holy Roman Emperor, who drowned in the Saleph River during the Third Crusade, burned Milan in the 12th century for constantly fighting with its neighbors.",
        "answer": [
          "Frederick Barbarossa",
          "Frederick I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader from this modern-day country granted William Knox D'Arcy the exclusive right to its oil in a 1901 \"concession.\" A Russian-trained Cossack Brigade assisted Mozaffer ad-Din, a shah of this country's Qajar dynasty. An American named Howard Baskerville was killed during a siege of this country's city of Tabriz, and this country's Pahlavi dynasty was deposed following an Islamic Revolution led by the exiled Ruhollah Khomeini [[koh-MAY- nee]]. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country, formerly called Persia.",
        "answer": [
          "Islamic Republic of Iran",
          "Persia before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "For his international influence, the Ayatollah Khomeini was named this magazine's \"Man of the Year\" in 1979.",
        "answer": "Time"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, a set of six semicircular earthworks constructed by Native Americans form the center of the Poverty Point World Heritage Site. The \"Red River of the South\" once formed part of the U.S.-Mexico border in this state and flows past this state's third-largest city, located mostly in Caddo Parish. This state's Jean Lafitte National Historical Park and Preserve often features reenactments of battles from the War of 1812. For ten points, the French Quarter is the oldest neighborhood of a city in which Mardi Gras is celebrated in what U.S. state?",
        "answer": "Louisiana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "New Orleans is on the southern shore of this shallow lake whose flooding caused catastrophic damage during Hurricane Katrina in 2005.",
        "answer": "Lake Pontchartrain 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A lullaby first called “A Time for Tony” inspired the theme song of this program of which Jeff Probst hosted a \"Rock & Roll\" spin-off. Art Fleming was the host of this show when John McCain appeared twice in 1965 but declined Merv Griffin's request to host this program's revival in 1984. In 2003, this program's producers removed a rule limiting contestants to five appearances, enabling a 74-win streak by Ken Jennings. For ten points, name this program which was hosted by Alex Trebek until his death in 2020.",
        "answer": "Jeopardy!"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1984, after Merv Griffin brought Jeopardy! back to the air, this former nightclub singer and game show host took over as announcer on Alex Trebek's recommendation and made a name for himself with the phrase \"This is Jeopardy!.\"",
        "answer": "John \"Johnny\" Gilbert"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A secret 1915 treaty signed in this city established Italy as a member of the Allies. An 1839 agreement signed in this city inspired one diplomat to express his disbelief that one country would fight a war over \"a scrap of paper.\" A 1930 conference in this city aimed to update the Washington Naval Treaty signed eight years earlier. Belgian neutrality was affirmed in, for ten points, what capital city of an empire upon which the sun supposedly never set?",
        "answer": "London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The leading U.S. negotiator of the 1922 Washington Naval Treaty was this Secretary of State who had previously served on the Supreme Court and later returned to the Court as Chief Justice.",
        "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A vice-presidential candidate in this election year claimed that one opponent’s victory would lead to rule by a “semi-barbarous race” who would “subject the white women to their unbridled lust.\" In this election year, Francis P. Blair was the losing vice-presidential candidate on the ticket of Horatio Seymour, who had faced draft riots in New York five years prior. An impeachment was held in this year for violation of the Tenure of Office Act which had passed in the previous year. For ten points, name this election year of the first presidential victory for Ulysses S. Grant.",
        "answer": "1868"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1868 election, three states had yet to be restored to the Union and were not allowed to take part in the election. Those three states were Texas, Mississippi, and what other state for which the military appointed Henry H. Wells as governor in 1868?",
        "answer": "Virginia 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Civil Rights",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City in which Martin Luther King, Jr. was assassinated.",
          "answer": "Memphis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Speech given by MLK at the 1963 March on Washington.",
          "answer": "\"I Have a Dream\""
        },
        {
          "question": "President who signed the 1964 Civil Rights Act into law.",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama city known for its bus boycott and a march from Selma.",
          "answer": "Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Activist group that rode interstate buses to protest non-enforcement of desegregation laws.",
          "answer": "Freedom Riders"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of students including Elizabeth Eckford who were denied entry to an Arkansas high school.",
          "answer": "Little Rock Nine"
        },
        {
          "question": "40-year president of the National Council of Negro Women.",
          "answer": "Dorothy Height"
        },
        {
          "question": "Six-year-old subject of Norman Rockwell's The Problem We All Live With.",
          "answer": "Ruby Bridges 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1 The Catholic Monarchs of Spain"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "With regard to King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the with regard to king ferdinand and queen isabella, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Holy Office\" established in 1478 to ensure that converted Jews and Muslims did not revert to their previous faiths.",
          "answer": "The Spanish Inquisition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two kingdoms which entered into de facto unification under their joint rule.",
          "answer": "Castile and Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which the kingdom of Granada was conquered.",
          "answer": "1492"
        },
        {
          "question": "Grandson who became Holy Roman Emperor.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles V or Carlos V",
            "Charles I of Spain",
            "Carlos I of Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dominican friar of Jewish ancestry, named Grand Inquisitor during their reign.",
          "answer": "Tomás de Torquemada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fifth daughter, wife to Arthur, Prince of Wales, and then later to his brother.",
          "answer": "Catherine of Aragon or Catalina de Aragón"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal dynasty begun by Henry II from which both of them were descended.",
          "answer": "House of Trastámara"
        },
        {
          "question": "General called El Gran Capitán for his actions during the conquest of Granada and the Italian Wars.",
          "answer": [
            "Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba",
            "1st Duke of Santángelo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canals",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Canal obstructed in March 2021 by the barge Ever Given.",
          "answer": "Suez Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Italian city-state known for its many canals.",
          "answer": [
            "Venice",
            "Comune di Venezia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese canal which links the Yellow and Yangtze rivers.",
          "answer": "Jing–Hang Grand Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jutland [[JUT-lund]] canal formerly named for Kaiser Wilhelm.",
          "answer": "Kiel Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two Russian rivers connected by a canal named for Vladimir Lenin.",
          "answer": "Volga and Don Rivers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central British city connected to Worsley by the Bridgewater Canal, built to export coal in 1761.",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian pharaoh whose namesake canal connected the Nile to the Red Sea.",
          "answer": [
            "Necho II",
            "Neku, Nekau,",
            "Nikuu in place of Necho"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rhine tributary that Charlemagne attempted to connect to the Danube.",
          "answer": "Main ] River 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "This tribe was the primary audience for Elias Boudinot's Phoenix newspaper. A minority party within this tribe signed the Treaty of New Echota [[eh-KOH-tah]] that, despite the lack of approval from (*) John Ross, led to an event they called Nu na da ul tsun yi. Samuel Worcester argued that a law requiring non-natives to have a license to be on land belonging to this tribe was unconstitutional. This tribe rapidly became more (*) literate after Sequoyah created their syllabary. For ten points, name this Native American tribe who were removed from Georgia by way of the Trail of Tears."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cherokee",
        "Tsalagi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One woman from what is today this country was named Isabella, known as the \"First Lady of the World,\" and persuaded Louis XII to not send troops against her home city. After the Palaiologos started to die out, a cadet branch ruled the March of (20 pts)",
        "Montferrat in what is now this country. Napoleon defeated an attack under General of the Artillery Joseph Alvinczi, in the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Rivoli in what is now this country. The location of the Rotonda di San Lorenzo of Matilda of Tuscany, for ten points, what is this modern country, the home of Vincenzo II Gonzaga, Duke of Mantua?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Italy",
        "Italian Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's poetry collections, In the Winter of Cities and Androgyne, Mon Amour, explore his sexuality and his lost childhood as the son of an alcoholic traveling shoe salesman. This writer's sister, Rose, is thought to be the model for some of his (20 pts)",
        "characters, including Laura Wingfield, and her lobotomy is represented in his work (10 pts)",
        "Suddenly, Last Summer. Considered one of the greatest American playwrights, for ten points, who was this writer of the Pulitzer Prize-winning works Cat on a Hot Tin Roof and A Streetcar Named Desire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tennessee Williams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) León Gieco [[hee-EH-koh]] dedicated a song to this country's outlaws titled \"Rural Bandits.\" A French-born pirate who fought for this country captured Monterey, California for six days and was named (20 pts)",
        "Hippolyte Bouchard [[ee-poh-LEET boo- SHARD]]. Before he was killed in Bolivia, outlaw Butch Cassidy fled to this country. A folk hero from this country, Juan (10 pts)",
        "Moreira, was robbed by a grocery store owner named Sardetti. For ten points, name this South American country known for its gaucho cowboys."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Argentina",
        "Argentine Republic",
        "República Argentina 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) About a thousand people from throughout the Middle East are thought to have gathered annually at this ancient Mesopotamian site. Scientists have identified the wild wheat growing around this site as the closest relative to the wheat (20 pts)",
        "we eat today, suggesting that celebrations there were a step towards the domestication of crops. Discovered in 1994 by Klaus (10 pts)",
        "Schmidt, this site may have been the location of one of the first temples in human history, built between 10,000 and 12,000 years ago. For ten points, name this Neolithic archaeological site in southeastern Turkey."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Göbekli Tepe ] or Potbelly Hill",
        "or Girê Mirazan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A blizzard delayed one army at this battle from commencing its attack on February 12. A rallying cry at this battle, which echoed a similar cry from the 15th century, translated to \"we’ll (20 pts)",
        "get them.\" Sylvain Raynal’s troops went for days without water at this battle before surrendering Fort Vaux [[VOH]]. The Nivelle Offensive occurred at this battle, at which one side intended to “bleed [the French] white” by forcing counteroffensives. (10 pts)",
        "Philippe Pétain [[peh-TAHN]] became known as the lion of, for ten points, what lengthy World War One battle fought in France?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Verdun",
        "Bataille de Verdun",
        "Schlacht um Verdun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The western third of this island was ceded from Spain to France in the 1697 Treaty of Ryswick. Leaders of this island's indigenous population, including Hatuey [[ah-TWAY]], took the title cacique [[kah-SEE-keh]]. After (20 pts)",
        "Christopher Columbus landed on this island on December 6, 1492, the native Taino [[TIE-noh]] people were divided into five chiefdoms and subjected to slavery. In 1806, troops under General (10 pts)",
        "Henri Christophe attempted to seize the entirety of this island from the French. For ten points, name this Caribbean island divided between two countries."
      ],
      "answer": "Hispaniola"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The \"Lavender Scare\" occurred concurrently with an event spearheaded by this man, who often used homosexuality as a smear tactic in his campaigns. Roy Cohn was this man's chief counsel during a series of hearings involving this man and the U.S. (20 pts)",
        "Army. The suicide of Senator Lester C. Hunt badly hurt this man's reputation, leading to his (10 pts)",
        "censure by the Senate in 1954. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who is infamous for alleging that Communist spies infiltrated the U.S. government, sparking the Second Red Scare."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" McCarthy 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 1"
    }
  ]
}